Guide to the Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas papers, 1848-1906 and undated RL.10043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas papers
1848-1978 and undated, bulk 1848-1889
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas, Ella Gertrude Clanton
RL.10043
2 Linear Feet
Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas was the wife of Jefferson Thomas, Confederate officer and Georgia planter. This collection contains diaries, partially unbound, for the years 1848-1849, 1851-1852, 1855-1859, 1861-1866, 1868-1871, and 1878-1889, with the first volume in a different hand from the rest. Typed copies of the diaries are also included. The entries describe in detail Mrs. Thomas' reading; studies at Macon Female College (now called Wesleyan College) in Macon, Ga.; conversion to methodism; clothing and dress styles; gossip and social life; shopping and prices; church services; courtship by and marriage to Jefferson Thomas; and plantation life in Burke and Columbia counties.
Biographical note
Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas was born on April 4 1834, the daughter of a prosperous property and plantation owner. She attended Macon Female College (now called Wesleyan College) in Macon, Georgia when she was 15, and was an avid reader throughout her life. She married her husband Jefferson Thomas, also a plantation owner in 1852 and they lived outside of Augusta, Georgia and had several children. Following the war, the Thomases moved to Augusta as a result of finacial hardship.
Collection Overview
This collection contains diaries, partially unbound, for the years 1848-1849, 1851-1852, 1855-1859, 1861-1866, 1868-1871, and 1878-1889, with the first volume in a different hand from the rest. Typed version of the diaries are also included. The entries describe in detail Mrs. Thomas' reading; studies at Macon Female College (now called Wesleyan College) in Macon, Ga.; conversion to methodism; clothing and dress styles; gossip and social life; shopping and prices; church services; courtship by and marriage to Jefferson Thomas; and plantation life in Burke and Columbia counties.
Other subjects discussed include black religion; the institution of slavery and the relations between white men and slave women; Civil War military activities, especially concerning Jefferson Thomas' career; destruction of property by Union troops; social conditions after the war; spiritualism; labor and servant problems, financial losses and poverty; school teaching; and the earthquake of 1886.
Other items include letters (two from Jefferson Thomas); photograph of a portrait of Mrs. Thomas; and a life membership certificate from the National Woman Suffrage Association of the United States (later the National American Woman Suffrage Association).
Provenance
The Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1956 and 1978.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Spiritualism -- United States; Methodists -- Georgia; Plantation life -- Georgia; Courtship -- Southern States; Slavery -- Georgia; Earthquakes -- Southern States; African Americans -- Religion; Costume -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Georgia -- Social life and customs; Women -- Southern States -- Social conditions; Confederate States of America -- Social conditions; Women -- Education -- Southern States; Women -- Southern States -- Diaries; Thomas, Ella Gertrude Clanton; Thomas, Jefferson; National American Woman Suffrage Association; Wesleyan College (Macon, Ga.); Confederate States of America. Army -- Officers
- Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas papers, 1848-1906 and undated; 1
  - Diary, 1848-1852; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1855-1856 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1856-1859 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1861-1864 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1864-1866 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1868-1870 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1870-1871 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1878-1880 (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1881-1889 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1865 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1879-1882 (Box 2)
  - Photocopies of letters, National American Woman Suffrage Association, clippings and other documents, 1882-1902, 1978 and undated (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1848-1849 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1851 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1852 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1852 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1852 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1855-1856; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1856-1859 (Box 2)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1861-1864; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1864-1866; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1868-1870; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1870-1871; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1878-1880; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Diary (Typed Copy), 1881-1889 (Box 4)
  - Loose Photocopy and Photograph of a Portrait, 1978 and undated (Box 4)